<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Experience Design in the Open Hybrid Cloud</title>
    <description>How does if feel currently to experience the Open Hybrid Cloud? What do users see today and how can we design for the future?</description>
    <link>http://localhost:4000/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:4000/sitemap.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/>
    <pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 17:32:58 -0400</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 17:32:58 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.9.0</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Running an Example Node.js Kubernetes based Application with the new Developer Sandbox for Red Hat OpenShift</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’m a Product Designer at Red Hat. Every day I must consider “How can we improve the experience for our users?”. Let me share my experience with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.redhat.com/developer-sandbox&quot;&gt;new Developer Sandbox for Red Hat OpenShift&lt;/a&gt;. In my opinion it’s an excellent step towards improving our Developer’s Experience of using OpenShift.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might be wondering “who is this Developer persona?” that we are serving with this Sandbox environment. A lot of the features of the OpenShift Developer Console target a DevOps Engineer. This person may be exploring what it would mean for their team to transition to a containerized deployment. It could be argued that an IT Decision Maker like an IT Manager or Director, an Architect, or a trailblazing Application Developer are personas that are also targeted with this Sandbox.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s walk through the process of launching your Developer Sandbox for Red Hat OpenShift. Then I’ll take you through the process of deploying an example Node.js application.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;first-request-your-developer-sandbox-for-red-hat-openshift&quot;&gt;First: Request your Developer Sandbox for Red Hat OpenShift.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What does it mean to have a Developer Sandbox? You’ll get Developer access to an OpenShift cluster at zero charge for 30 days.  If you’d like to follow along, you can &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.redhat.com/developer-sandbox&quot;&gt;request a Sandbox of your own&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/developer-sandbox.png&quot; alt=&quot;Developer Sandbox&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order to launch a Sandbox, you will need to create a Red Hat account or if you already have one, log in to your existing account. Once you have requested a Sandbox, logging in is a breeze since you make use of your Red Hat account. Make sure you select to log in as the “DevSandbox” user. The “OpenShift_SRE” user is the login that the team ensuring your cluster remains running and functional uses to administer things :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;second-enjoy-a-guided-tour-of-the-developer-console&quot;&gt;Second: Enjoy a guided tour of the Developer Console.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now that you are logged in, you can walk through a quick guided tour of the Developer perspective of the Console. (Of course if you wish, you can skip this!) In this tour you will get a better grounding around where you might go for Monitoring, how to Search for resources, and how to get Help if you need further assistance. You’ll also learn about the Perspective switcher that will allow you to switch from the Developer perspective to the Administrator perspective. While you do have access to this Administrator area of the console, you won’t be able to see and manage EVERYTHING a user with Admin privileges would be able to.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/welcome-dev-perspective.png&quot; alt=&quot;Developer Perspective Welcome&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/guided-tour.png&quot; alt=&quot;Guided Tour&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;third-get-a-sample-application-up-and-running&quot;&gt;Third: Get a sample application up and running.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now let’s get an application running. I recommend starting with creating a sample application to get a feel for what you can do ultimately with your own application. Within the “Topology” section, there is a card that lists out a few “Quick Starts”. The first link allows you to work through a tutorial on creating a sample application. Click that link to find that a side panel slides out with a few steps to follow.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/select-quickstart.png&quot; alt=&quot;Select Quickstart&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the instructions in the quick start, you’ll notice a number of choice you’d be able to make if you wanted to get started using a code sample. In this case we will follow the quick start’s lead and select Node.js.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/select-nodejs.png&quot; alt=&quot;Select Node.js&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since we are making use of the sample, we can go ahead and accept the defaults that have been filled in on the form. This is where if you are deploying your own Node.js application you could point to your own Git Repo.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/create-application.png&quot; alt=&quot;Create Application&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s as simple as that! The application will take just a few seconds to spin up and the donut chart around the Node.js logo will turn from a light blue to a darker blue signifying there is a pod running.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/application-created.png&quot; alt=&quot;Application Created&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;fourth-dig-in-a-bit-deeper-to-get-to-know-the-details-of-your-application&quot;&gt;Fourth: Dig in a bit deeper to get to know the details of your application.&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are following the quick start, you can continue on to get an understanding of a few extra pieces around your application running. There are a few icons surrounding the Node.js logo that we should explore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the bottom left, there is an icon that represents the build status. Hovering over it will give you a quick textual status and clicking it will drill into the log for the build that has run. Typically, you’d really only need to navigate in this far if something seems like it’s gone wrong with the build.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/build-status.png&quot; alt=&quot;Build Status&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/build-logs.png&quot; alt=&quot;Build Logs&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the bottom right, there is an icon that represents the source code location. Hovering over it will give you a quick textual hint that you can access the code and clicking it will drill into the source code for editing. In the case of this sample running on the OpenShift Developer Sandbox, it opens up &lt;a href=&quot;https://developers.redhat.com/products/codeready-workspaces/overview&quot;&gt;Red Hat CodeReady Workspaces&lt;/a&gt; which is an OpenShift-native developer workspace server and IDE.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/source-code.png&quot; alt=&quot;Source Code&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/crw.png&quot; alt=&quot;CodeReady Workspaces&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, in the top right, there is an icon that represents the URL to your running application. Hovering over it will guide you towards opening the URL and clicking it will open the application in a new tab. In this case we get to see the sample application output running which gives even more guidance around developing with OpenShift.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/open-url.png&quot; alt=&quot;Open URL&quot; /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/application.png&quot; alt=&quot;Application&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s it for the quick tour of creating an example application making use of the OpenShift Developer Sandbox. If you fall into the category of any type of Developer, I’d encourage you to give it a shot and I’d love to hear any feedback you have. Feel free to &lt;a href=&quot;https://lizsurette.github.io/about/&quot;&gt;send me an email&lt;/a&gt;! It’s always great to hear how we might be able to make improvements on user experience.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/open%20hybrid%20cloud/kubernetes/openshift/nodejs/2021/04/01/example-kubernetes-on-openshift-sandbox.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/open%20hybrid%20cloud/kubernetes/openshift/nodejs/2021/04/01/example-kubernetes-on-openshift-sandbox.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>open hybrid cloud</category>
        
        <category>kubernetes</category>
        
        <category>openshift</category>
        
        <category>nodejs</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Hello Again, World</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;I’ve decided that I’m going to start blogging again. Previously, I had written all about my design work with OpenStack and a bit about the oVirt community work I did. Since then, I’ve worked on a number of different projects including OpenShift and have recently transitioned to thinking about the Open Hybrid Cloud experience broadly. I’ll be sharing my stories as I enter and design for this brave new world. Stay tuned for more posts.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 17 Mar 2021 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/personal/open%20hybrid%20cloud/2021/03/17/hello-world.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/personal/open%20hybrid%20cloud/2021/03/17/hello-world.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>personal</category>
        
        <category>open hybrid cloud</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>Findings from Reviewing the oVirt Overall Dashboard Concept at Red Hat Summit</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was originally written and shared on August 5, 2015 when I was working with the oVirt Community.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.redhat.com/summit/&quot;&gt;Red Hat Summit&lt;/a&gt; this past year, we presented a few concepts that we hope to include as features in oVirt.NEXT. One of those concepts was a design for an overall dashboard. This dashboard would aggregate all of the data from within an environment (all data centers) and present the user with visualizations of this information. The following is the initial design concept for the overall dashboard that we showed:
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/overall-dashboard.png&quot; alt=&quot;Overall Dashboard&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We talked to about a dozen people at Summit as they visited our locations in Customer Central as well as Community Central and asked them to give their initial reactions to the design. The questions that we focused on were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What do you like with this design?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What could be improved with this design?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is there anything missing in this design?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is there anything that could be taken away to simplify this design?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A list of the top findings that we came away with are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;This dashboard needs to be broken down to focus on each Data Center to be really useful. An example that I talked to one user about is how currently we show that there is 300GB of free storage. If the user wants to create a storage domain and allocate 150GB to it they need to know which Data Center to create that Storage Domain in. If Data Center 1 has 200GB free and Data Center 2 has 100GB free, there is currently no way to know that the user should create this Storage Domain in Data Center 1. If they try to create it in Data Center 2 they will be unsuccessful.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The “Most Utilized” lists will be EXTREMELY useful. They are a must-keep.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Perhaps the data that makes up the Health statistics could be filtered for just within last day. This way the user could see these and know that if a change occurs it is something they should take a look at right away.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;The differences between the Storage in Utilization and the Storage Capacity area could be explained better. More research and design is needed to work these details out to make it clear to the user.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Users really liked seeing trends. The radial graphs with trends for history will be very helpful while monitoring oVirt environments.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on this feedback that we got from our users, we have a clear path on the updates that we’d like to make to this design. Stay tuned for the next version! If you have any feedback of your own, please feel free to leave a comment below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks,
Liz&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 05 Aug 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/virtualization/2015/08/05/ovirt-dashboard-findings.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/virtualization/2015/08/05/ovirt-dashboard-findings.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>virtualization</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>A fresh look for the oVirt Administrator Portal Dashboard</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was originally written and shared on June 18, 2015 when I was working with the oVirt Community.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next major release of &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ovirt.org/Home&quot;&gt;oVirt&lt;/a&gt;, we have been putting some thought into updating the Dashboard for the Administrator Portal. The goal for this update would be to allow admins to quickly glance at the state of their environment, see the metrics that are most important to them, and then jump off to dig even deeper from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step in our design efforts was to research what exists today in the oVirt Administrator Portal as well as other virtualization administration UIs out there and decide which of this information might make sense to surface on a dashboard. We did an initial mock-up based on this research so that we could show people and get some first glance reactions.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/ovirt-dashboard-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;oVirt Dashboard 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After running this initial mockup by a few people who know the virtualization space well, we put together and sent out a &lt;a href=&quot;https://docs.google.com/forms/d/1nGMgjHeWszisxWAuiV5eCahW_-OK_ytIiCpwEx_gFQE/viewform&quot;&gt;survey&lt;/a&gt; to the oVirt community &lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/ovirt/status/601452731493011456&quot;&gt;asking for feedback&lt;/a&gt; from any and all administrators on what they’d like to see on a dashboard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After excellent feedback in both areas, we were able to bring everything together that we’d learned and landed on a more polished first cut of what the oVirt.next Administrator Portal Dashboard could look like.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/ovirt-dashboard-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;oVirt Dashboard 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We are still looking to gather feedback on the first round of this dashboard design. Please feel free to leave your thoughts in a comment below. Are you going to be attending &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.redhat.com/summit/&quot;&gt;Red Hat Summit&lt;/a&gt; this year? Stop by the oVirt booth in Community Central on Wednesday or Thursday if you want to take a closer look and give your feedback in person. We are working on a few other concepts that we will be sharing there as well, so come help shape the future direction of the oVirt Administrator Portal!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks,
Liz&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/virtualization/2015/06/18/fresh-look-oVirt-admin-portal.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/virtualization/2015/06/18/fresh-look-oVirt-admin-portal.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>virtualization</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The OpenStack Years: Streamlining the Install of OpenStack with the RDO Manager UI</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was originally written and shared on June 10, 2015 when I was working with the OpenStack Community.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was &lt;a href=&quot;http://greenstack.die.upm.es/2015/06/10/streamlining-the-install-of-openstack-with-the-rdo-manager-ui/&quot;&gt;featured on GreenStack&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before being able to use everything that OpenStack has to offer, you need to be able to install it. The installation step of OpenStack has been a heavily talked about topic over the last few years. Whether you are a developer or tester trying to get your environment up and running or an end user trying to use OpenStack to spin up VMs, you’ve most likely put a fair amount of time into the install and configuration step. Since it’s the first thing every user experiences with OpenStack we really need to make it as effortless as possible. OpenStack is an interesting beast because there are so many pieces to the project (some being optional) which make configuration very tricky. We’ve set out to reduce the frustration from a user’s point of view as we designed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rdoproject.org/RDO-Manager&quot;&gt;RDO Manager&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since OpenStack is so complex, it’s difficult to design an installation and configuration UI that steps the user through every single setting. One of the main goals we had in designing the RDO Manager UI is to surface the common configuration parameters to the user and tuck away the rest. This way, the novice user could install and configure their cloud without having to dig. The advanced user could dig a little deeper and get into additional settings that they might want to control. Designing the UI this way requires talking with as many people as possible who will use this application to install OpenStack so that we are sure we surface the most important configuration options. We are still learning more as new people use RDO Manager and give us feedback. The following is a walkthrough of the current design of the Overview page of the RDO Manager UI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For all users, when they log into the RDO Manager UI they will first see the Overview page. From this view, the user should be able to do everything they need to for a simple OpenStack install. On the right, they will see a checklist to follow as they complete the necessary steps to plan their cloud deployment. Once they have fulfilled each step, they will be ready to deploy their cloud.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/checklist.png&quot; alt=&quot;Checklist&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing a user will do to begin the planning process is register nodes. This is the hardware that will run the cloud. Clicking on “Register Nodes” will bring up a modal dialog for the user to either register nodes manually, or upload a set of nodes from a file such as a CSV.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/register-nodes.png&quot; alt=&quot;Register Nodes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We’ve designed this modal to allow for registering multiple nodes at once so that the user doesn’t have to continue to come back into this modal for each additional node they’d like to register. Uploading a CSV file will populate the nodes from that file in a list on the left of the modal. The user can edit any parameters they wish before clicking “Register Nodes”.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/register-nodes-modal.png&quot; alt=&quot;Register Nodes Modal&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As nodes are registered, they will drop into groups (or Node Profiles) based on the their hardware specifications. This will make it easier to identify which nodes should be assigned to perform Compute, Controller, or Storage functions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the nodes have been registered, the user will want to define their network configuration. In the first version of RDO Manager, there will be templates provided to create the networks, generate IP addresses for each node, and configure the services to run on the appropriate networks. Users will be able to edit this configuration file within a modal in the UI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before assigning deployment roles to nodes, the user may need to provide configuration details for some of the roles. This configuration includes things such as the provisioning image and service configuration for each role.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/edit-role.png&quot; alt=&quot;Edit Role&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Editing the service configuration will apply these parameters to the underlying services running on a node with this deployment role. This is where the most work has been needed to be sure we surface the most important configuration and hide away the advanced parameters so that we can keep it as simple as possible for the user.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/edit-role-modal.png&quot; alt=&quot;Edit Role Modal&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assigning deployment roles to nodes is the last step in the checklist before the user can Verify and Deploy their environment. Users can either drag and drop roles onto node profiles or they can click the “+” to assign a role to a number of nodes. After assigning a role, the user can choose how many nodes they would like from the node profile to take on that deployment role.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/assign-roles.png&quot; alt=&quot;Assign Roles&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the user has met all of the requirements in the checklist, they can click the Verify and Deploy button to kick off the deployment of their cloud.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/verify-and-deploy.png&quot; alt=&quot;Verify and Deploy&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you think about this design so far? Feel free to leave your thoughts in a comment below :) In a following post, I will cover the initial design thinking around monitoring the environment during and after deployment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will you be at &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.redhat.com/summit/&quot;&gt;Red Hat Summit&lt;/a&gt; this year and want to try RDO Manager out? Come to the RDO Booth in the Community Central area and I will have a system running for you to poke at and give comments on. I’d love to get your feedback in person!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks!
Liz&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2015 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/openstack/2015/06/10/streamlining-openstack-install.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/openstack/2015/06/10/streamlining-openstack-install.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>openstack</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The OpenStack Years: Moving forward as a User Experience Team in the OpenStack Juno release cycle</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was originally written and shared on June 13, 2014 when I was working daily with the OpenStack Community.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This post was &lt;a href=&quot;https://superuser.openstack.org/articles/moving-forward-as-a-user-experience-team-in-the-openstack-juno-release-cycle/&quot;&gt;featured on superuser.openstack.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;OpenStack Juno Summit in Atlanta was a major turning point for User Experience professionals working on OpenStack. Not only did we have 3 specific design sessions around UX work and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.openstack.org/summit/openstack-summit-atlanta-2014/session-videos/presentation/user-experience-in-the-openstack-community&quot;&gt;1 talk on the persona work we’ve done&lt;/a&gt;, all with great attendance, but we’ve committed to a number of actions we will be taking over the course of the Juno development cycle. All of these actions will improve User Experience work within the OpenStack community and the best part is that we will be working as a team to do this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;better-communication&quot;&gt;Better Communication…&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first session that we had at Summit around UX was an hour and a half long design session to talk about all things User Experience. It was great to have almost everyone working on design and user focused work in one room together brainstorming on how we can work better as a team moving forward now that there are more than 2 of us :) One major step forward that we agreed on is that we will start &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Meetings/UX&quot;&gt;meeting bi-weekly over IRC&lt;/a&gt;. We had our first meeting already and the communication channel is so much better already. There were just about 15 people who attended (a mixture of developers and designers) representing at least 7 different companies that I’m aware of. We covered a few basic topics during the first meeting such as a standing schedule of times for future meetings. But this meeting will eventually be important for us all to be on the same page around what we are designing towards for a specific release. We also invite anyone working on any project within OpenStack who may need some UX guidance. This gives a specific time and place that is published for anyone looking to get their requests on our radar.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;making-it-easy-for-folks-to-get-in-touch-with-the-ux-team&quot;&gt;Making it Easy for Folks to Get in Touch with the UX Team…&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coming to our bi-weekly meeting would be a great option. Also, if you prefer IRC and have something you’d like to contact us about right away you can find us in the #openstack-ux channel on Freenode. We agreed at summit that we will standardize on using the tag [UX] on the developer mailing list for communications as well, so if it’s an e-mail you’d like to craft and send, adding this tag to the subject line will be sure to get our attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;prioritizing-work-on-the-ui-cli-and-api&quot;&gt;Prioritizing work on the UI, CLI, and API…&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A big topic within the UX team currently is around how we can be sure to evangelize User Experience work that can be done for projects that don't include a UI. We’d love to be able to contribute resources with 100% focus on UX work towards CLI and API efforts, but we unfortunately don’t have anyone with bandwidth to take this on currently. We are thinking it would be a good idea to reach out to folks in each project to be sure they know how UX could help with things like consistency of CLIs and APIs. If there is anyone currently working on these projects who have interest in UX type work, it would be great to connect with them and help drive forward their current UX efforts. Keep an eye out for more discussion on this topic within each of the teams. Also, if you currently work on a team and are interested in bringing more UX focus to CLIs, APIs, or anything else, let us know and we can do our best to help out!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tracking-ux-tasks&quot;&gt;Tracking UX Tasks…&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;UX tasks are a bit unique in the way that the outcome of the tasks normally influence tasks that already exist or need to be created in other projects. &lt;a href=&quot;https://storyboard.openstack.org/#!/&quot;&gt;Storyboard&lt;/a&gt; is a tool that has been created within the OpenStack community that is being designed and developed based on the OpenStack task tracking process needs. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/StoryBoard&quot;&gt;Storyboard team&lt;/a&gt; has been amazing to work with and have been really interested in getting feedback from all of their users and potential users (including the UX team!). They are currently focusing on the features that are needed for users to transition over to using StoryBoard. The UX team has some requirements that are different from other projects (such as attaching images to stories) but the Storyboard team has been very responsive to getting these features in for us. We have already decided to move over to using Storyboard as a way to track out work as soon as a few infrastructure issues have been ironed out. This will be a great way to continue to give early feedback to the team as they solidify the first version of Storyboard for all of their end users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-standard-design-review-tool&quot;&gt;A Standard Design Review Tool…&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve been attempting to find a great design review tool that we can all use to share and get feedback on our designs as a team. We haven’t had any luck with finding a great open source tool for this, but we are still searching. One tool that we’ve considered using is called &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.invisionapp.com/&quot;&gt;InVision&lt;/a&gt;. With this tool, we can upload images and keep revision history of images. Reviewers can come in and view these images and provide feedback directly on the images in the place that the comment applies. A conversation can then take place on this topic right inline to the design. Having one tool that everyone can subscribe to would make it easy to take our design communication to the next step. If you have any suggestions on open source design review tools, please let us know! In the meantime, we will continue to use a mixture of InVision and the mailing list to get feedback on our designs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;a-standard-design-tool&quot;&gt;A Standard Design Tool?…&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We talked a little bit about whether we need to standardize on one tool for design work or not. We all ultimately agreed that since there are a lot of stages of designs (ranging from sketching to high fidelity) and people have preferences and access to different design tools it makes sense to not standardize on one tool, but rather to have design template files for a number of different tools that folks can use. This file would include all of the basic design elements used in Horizon designs today. We will most likely start with templates for tools that a few of the very active designers are using (InDesign, Balsamiq, and maybe Axure). If there is a designer who starts contributing in the community and wants to use a new tool, they could put together a template for that tool and contribute that to the community as a first step. These templates will eventually live on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/UX&quot;&gt;UX wiki&lt;/a&gt; for designer consumption.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;juno-design-priorities&quot;&gt;Juno Design Priorities…&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we had a few design sessions within the Horizon track, we were able to discuss some of the specific design work that we’ve been doing and would like to continue working on through the Juno cycle. We &lt;a href=&quot;https://etherpad.openstack.org/p/juno-summit-horizon-usability-test-results&quot;&gt;discussed&lt;/a&gt; the results that we got from running the baseline Horizon Usability Testing and all agreed that we should continue to make design proposal updates for the Launch Instance Workflow, Error Messaging Guidelines, and Inline Help Guidelines within Horizon. We also proposed some ideas about improving the Overview Pages within Horizon. This work will continue to move forward this release based on &lt;a href=&quot;https://etherpad.openstack.org/p/juno-summit-overview-page-horizon&quot;&gt;feedback&lt;/a&gt; from the Horizon developers and operators in attendance. Another big focus during the Juno cycle will be around &lt;a href=&quot;https://etherpad.openstack.org/p/juno-summit-horizon-tuskar-ui&quot;&gt;finding the right place for the Tuskar UI work&lt;/a&gt; that has been done. This UI is starting to touch more components than just Horizon and TripleO and will continue to grow throughout the next release. And of course, we will continue to push our &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Personas&quot;&gt;Persona work&lt;/a&gt; forward and strive towards having a final first set of personas to use as we design new features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This isn’t an exhaustive list of things we plan to accomplish in the Juno release cycle, and some of these will continue throughout releases moving forward. But I’m proud of the incredible progress we’ve made as a new group that is still forming within such a large community of lots of projects. Are there items that you think the UX team should get involved with in the community? Drop me a note if you think so and we can add in new stories to Storyboard :)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Best,
Liz&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 13 Jun 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/openstack/2014/06/13/moving-forward-in-juno.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/openstack/2014/06/13/moving-forward-in-juno.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>openstack</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The OpenStack Years: An explosion of User Experience discussions at the OpenStack Juno Summit</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was originally written and shared on May 6, 2014 when I was working daily with the OpenStack Community.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next week OpenStackers will be getting together in person for the Juno Summit in Atlanta to plan out what exactly we think is important to deliver in the Juno release of OpenStack. I’m extremely happy to say that there are a number of sessions that are focused on talking through use cases, users, and User Experience efforts within OpenStack. I wanted to take some time to introduce the sessions that I plan to participate in with respect to UX and I hope to see any of you who are interested join me!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sessions 1 &amp;amp; 2 - &lt;a href=&quot;http://junodesignsummit.sched.org/event/e13c8775849567fe8576c16875d5c547#.U2ewpuZdXC4&quot;&gt;User Experience Designers Gathering&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; on the Cross-Project track
&lt;em&gt;Tuesday May 13, 2:50pm-4:20pm&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The last time I was at summit, it seemed like there were a lot of “Cross-project” topics that needed to be discussed in the design summit sessions. This year, the coordinators of these sessions made sure that there was a track set up for this type of discussion. Although they don’t specify one specific component of OpenStack, these talks are just as important as the core track sessions since they could actually contain one or more of the components. The User Experience group was lucky enough to get two of these session times back-to-back where we will have time to discuss moving ourselves forward as a group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this session we will try to get through as much as we can around the following topics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Introduction of everyone in the session.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What role do you have today?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;How does UX affect you?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;How will you (if you plan to) contribute to OpenStack UX?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;How active do you plan to be for the Juno development cycle?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Discussion of where are are currently in UX.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What components have we worked on so far?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What does our current process look like?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What tools do we use?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What has worked well?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What could be improved?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Discussion on where we want to go for Juno.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;How should we improve our process and tooling during the Juno release? How do we track this and who will take certain action items?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What tools should we remove/add?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What are our goals for UX during the Juno release? (More research/requirements work? More designing? More user testing?…) Which components will we focus on? (Horizon? Tuskar? Heat? Ceilometer?….) Which features will we focus on?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;UX as a program.
    &lt;ul&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;What does it mean to be a program?&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;li&gt;Would UX make sense to be a program? If so, how should we work together to make this something we could propose as a team?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;/ul&gt;
  &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The design summit sessions are separate from the main conference sessions. They happen in parallel, so you might need to make some hard decisions as a designer, developer, or operator on which talks vs. design sessions you attend. The great news is that mostly all of the talks given in the main conference are recorded and shared on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/user/OpenStackFoundation&quot;&gt;OpenStack Foundation youtube channel&lt;/a&gt; a few weeks after summit. Also, all of the design summit session notes will be tracked in &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Summit/Juno/Etherpads&quot;&gt;respective etherpads&lt;/a&gt;. You can find the etherpad for this specific session &lt;a href=&quot;https://etherpad.openstack.org/p/juno-summit-cross-project-user-experience&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Session 3 - &lt;a href=&quot;http://openstacksummitmay2014atlanta.sched.org/event/e19260fd989bb307e94b5a25558612f4#.U2eNceZdWG_&quot;&gt;User Experience in the OpenStack Community&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; as part of the main conference &lt;em&gt;Wednesday May 14, 3:30pm-4:10pm&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the one talk during the main conference that I will be delivering with 3 other UX professionals. It was exciting to me that this was accepted in the main conference since it showed that there is interest from the attendees in where we’ve been with User Experience so far in OpenStack and where we plan to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this talk we will be sharing our progress in the following areas:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Understanding the OpenStack users&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Requirements gathering&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Interaction design&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Design support during development&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Usability testing and feeding results back into new requirements&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We will also discuss the recent efforts, which build on Dave Neary’s previous work, to develop a set of personas to help the development community align with their users’ needs and tasks. We’ll review the methodology used to develop the personas, insights from the user interviews, and the personas created from the effort. Finally, we will provide recommendations and examples for how the community can effectively use the personas during their own planning, design, development, and testing efforts to improve the overall user experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Session 4 - &lt;a href=&quot;http://junodesignsummit.sched.org/event/db0c611f2dce2bf80df2287039c68d76#.U2ew2uZdWG8&quot;&gt;Review Horizon Usability Test feedback, proposals&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; on the Horizon track &lt;em&gt;Friday May 16, 9:00am-9:40am&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Back in March we conducted a set of baseline usability tests on the Horizon UI. My last blog post explained the process we took and reported out our findings. In this design session, we will quickly review these findings and then start discussing the design directions we’ve started to take on fixing these usability issues that were identified. The main proposals we will go through cover the following topics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fix Launch Instance workflow for end user and power user.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improve error messages and error message catalog.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Improve informational help information about form fields.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;http://lists.openstack.org/pipermail/openstack-dev/2014-April/033625.html&quot;&gt;discussion&lt;/a&gt; has been started on the development mailing list, so if you plan to attend this session, take a quick look at the history to familiarize yourself with the topics and designs we will be discussing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Session 5 - &lt;a href=&quot;http://junodesignsummit.sched.org/event/5114c75a9b7567d6bca752fcd0c28302#.U2ew3eZdWG8&quot;&gt;Dashboard Accessibility / Improving Overview Pages in Horizon&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; on the Horizon track &lt;em&gt;Friday May 16, 9:50am - 10:30am&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were so many great design summit proposals this time around, that our PTL suggested we try to combine a few so that each can have time during Summit for discussion. This session combines a talk around the current state and next steps of making sure the Horizon UI is accessible with an effort around improving the Overview pages in Horizon. Both topics encompass bringing a new level of maturity to the Horizon dashboard and focusing on needs of the end-user.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Accessibility talk will go through a &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Horizon/WebAccessibility&quot;&gt;wiki page&lt;/a&gt; of ideas around both improving accessibility as well as continuing to test for issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Overview page discussion time will be used to present some design options for using data from Ceilometer that would be shown to End Users or Administrators depending on their role. A few early concepts have been created and can be seen in the &lt;a href=&quot;http://junodesignsummit.sched.org/event/5114c75a9b7567d6bca752fcd0c28302#.U2ew3eZdWG8&quot;&gt;session schedule details&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Session 6 - &lt;a href=&quot;http://junodesignsummit.sched.org/event/056d1eccc8485910e62bed8c65f7a8e5#.U2ew3-ZdWG8&quot;&gt;Horizon Dev/Ops Session&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; on the Horizon track &lt;em&gt;Friday May 16, 10:50am-11:30am&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There has been feedback from operators who attended past summits that they didn’t feel welcome to attend any of the design summit sessions. The goal of these sessions is to allow for uninterrupted planning discussions for deciding what will be accomplished in the next release of OpenStack, but I know that the intention was not to shut operators out! Coordinators heard this feedback and are making sure that all operators feel welcome to come give their real-world feedback to developers as we work through planning the Juno release.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On top of this, Tom Fifield had the brilliant idea of setting aside some time for each track to have a specific discussion between operators and developers to be sure that developers understand the needs of their end-users. What are developers working on today that they need feedback on from operators? Where are there gaps in Horizon for operators today that developers need to put some focus on? I’m mostly looking forward to observing this discussion, but would love to make some contacts with operators for future usability testing and persona research efforts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you have any interest in User Experience in OpenStack, I highly recommend that you try to attend at least one of these sessions and get to know other designers and developers who are working in this space. Even if you are an end user or administrator of a cloud environment today and have some feedback for us, make sure you track us down!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Best,
Liz&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 06 May 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/openstack/2014/05/06/explosion-ux-juno-summit.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/openstack/2014/05/06/explosion-ux-juno-summit.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>openstack</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The OpenStack Years: Running a Baseline Usability Test on Horizon</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was originally written and shared on March 25, 2014 when I was working daily with the OpenStack Community.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over the last few months, I’ve been working with a group of folks from multiple companies on doing research around &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Personas#The_OpenStack_Personas_Working_Group&quot;&gt;building a set of Personas&lt;/a&gt; to present at the Atlanta Summit. In one of our first meetings, we talked about the need to do some &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Usability_testing&quot;&gt;usability testing&lt;/a&gt; as a separate effort from the Persona research. Earlier this month, a few of the folks from HP mentioned that they were hoping to run a usability test on the most recent (Icehouse) version of Horizon. This would be the first usability test within the community that I’m aware of and I was super excited that they were willing to let those of us interested to be a part of this testing effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The decision was made to focus this first round of testing on self-service end users of Horizon and write tasks for our participants to perform based on typical tasks these types of users often perform. NOTE: We would like to do more and more usability testing and continue to include other types of users and tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We started out by putting together a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.surveymonkey.com/s/R8QZ2RB&quot;&gt;screener&lt;/a&gt; to be sure that we got the correct people to test. Here’s a quick look at the questions that we asked:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What company do your work for?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How many people work for your organization worldwide? Please take into account all branches and locations.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What is the primary business or industry of your company?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What is your job title?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;What is your primary job role?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How many years have you performed system administration and/or network management/administration?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Do your PRIMARY job responsibilities include any of the following?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Do you manage or use cloud services?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Please select the cloud service providers and technologies that you have good working knowledge of.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Which of the following administration tasks do you perform at least once a month?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;In your daily software use as an IT professional, what percent of your time do you use?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Does your IT department currently offer cloud computing services at you company?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;How many virtual servers are there in your server environment?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Who owns the servers in your company?&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Please provide your email so we can potentially contact you for a study.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Please provide your first and last name.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Would you like us to consider you for other OpenStack community studies?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is one of the most important pieces to doing a usability test. It’s really important to be sure to test the users on tasks that they would actually perform in their daily work so that you get the best results possible. We kept the screener nice and short so that folks didn’t feel overwhelmed and could respond to the survey in just a few minutes. We actually ended up getting a really great response from the community mailing lists and LinkedIn on the screener. It was very encouraging as responses of people interested in participating in the testing started to flow in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As we sifted through the screener results, we took some time to write up the scenarios and tasks that each participant would go through. We made sure to list these in priority order since depending on time, we might not be able to get to each task with all of our users. Here’s a list of what the users would be doing during the testing:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scenario 1: Launching an instance&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Individual Tasks:
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Create a security key pair.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Create a network.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Boot from cirros image.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Confirm that instance was launched successfully.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scenario 2: Understand how many vCPUs are currently in use vs. how much quota is left.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Individual Tasks:
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Check out Overview Page to review current quota use/limit details.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scenario 3: Take a snapshot of an Instance to save for later use.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Individual Tasks:
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Either Launch an instance successfully, or identify a running instance in the instance view.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Choose to take a snapshot of that instance.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Confirm that the snapshot was successful.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scenario 4: Launch an instance from a snapshot.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Individual Tasks:
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Choose to either create an instance and boot from a snapshot, or identify a snapshot to create an instance from.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Confirm that the instance was started successfully.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Scenario 5: Launch an instance that boots from a specific volume.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Individual Tasks:
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Create a volume.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Launch an instance using Volume X as a boot source.&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, we were pretty much ready to run the tests. HP had a system running the latest and greatest version of Horizon that our users could access, it was just a matter of scheduling some time with a few of the people who responded to the screener. Scheduling can sometimes take a fair amount of time, but these users were extremely quick to respond. I wondered if that’s just the way it is with testing passionate open source software users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We didn’t record the testing, since we wanted to be sure that the identity of the participants was protected, but we did take a ton of notes during each of the tests to be sure we captured everything that went on both good and bad. Since there were a few of us who wanted to observe the testing and one person running the test, we used online meeting software in order to share the screen and audio during the test. We had a few hiccups with audio quality and definitely have areas that we could improve on for the next round of testing, but for a first test we got some awesome results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Throughout the testing, we found that the majority of the hour that we had with participants was taken up by the first task. This isn’t necessarily a bad thing, especially for a first time test within the community. There were a lot of findings that came out of “Launching your first Instance” since it is fairly broad and hit a lot of pieces of the UI. We did get to go through a few of the other scenarios with a few users as well for additional findings, but here’s where we ended up with the list of improvements that we can make:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;High Priority&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Improve error messages and error message catalog.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Fix Launch Instance workflow for end user and power user.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Improve informational help information about form fields.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Fix terminology. (e.g. launch instance, boot, shutoff, shutdown, etc.)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Show details for key pair and network in Launch Instance workflow.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Recommend a new Information Architecture.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Medium Priority&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Create UI guidelines (of best practices) for Developers to use.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Improve Online Help.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Provide clearer indication the application is working after clicking a button and the application doesn’t respond immediately.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Ensure consistency of network selection. (Drag and drop of networks very inconsistent from the other pieces of the launch instance modal)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Create consistency of visualizations and section of action button recommendations on Instance table.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Suggest defaults for the forms entry fields.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Provide Image information details during image selection.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Low Priority&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Allow users to edit the network an instance after launching instance.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Resolve confusion around the split inline actions button.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Explain what the Instance Boot Source field in Create Instance modal.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Provide description/high level information about flavors for flavor selection.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Make sorting clearer visually.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Provide solution for subnet checkbox to improve usability.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Nice to Have&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Provide “Save as Draft” option in the wizard.&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Change security group default name to “Default security group”.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that we’ve gathered a lot of great data, we will be focusing on how to make improvements to Horizon based initially on the high priority findings. This includes logging bugs and registering blueprints within Launchpad (both in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://launchpad.net/horizon&quot;&gt;Horizon&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://launchpad.net/openstack-ux&quot;&gt;User Experience&lt;/a&gt; spaces). The current plan is to come up with some proposal designs and have a &lt;a href=&quot;http://summit.openstack.org/cfp/details/32&quot;&gt;design session&lt;/a&gt; at the Atlanta Summit to create a plan for next steps on making sure Juno releases with features and improved functionality in Horizon that is important to our OpenStack users.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Tue, 25 Mar 2014 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/openstack/2014/03/25/horizon-baseline-usability-test.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/openstack/2014/03/25/horizon-baseline-usability-test.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>openstack</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The OpenStack Years: How does Horizon Stack up versus other Cloud Computing UIs?</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was originally written and shared on February 21, 2014 when I was working daily with the OpenStack Community.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One big part of designing a solution is understanding how the design compares to the other things out there that are similar. What has been done already? What are other users and designers doing in this space? In some cases, the design might be one of a kind, but in the case of Horizon, there are a fair amount of other players in the space. I took some time recently to look into some of the other UIs that exist. It gave me a good idea of how Horizon stacked up compared to these other UIs:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Netflix Asgard&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Windows Azure&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;PayPal Aurora&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;CloudStack&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Google Compute Engine&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Amazon Web Services&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This exercise gave me some great inspiration for improvements that could be made to Horizon. What are others doing out there to solve the needs that Horizon can’t solve for users? How can we improve Horizon to meet these needs? Here are some of the things that I noticed from a design perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;netflix-asgard&quot;&gt;Netflix Asgard&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you’ve used OpenStack enough, you know that certain tables begin to grow to be extremely large. Currently, there is a filter function on the Instances table within Horizon, but it’s not quite as slick as the one that is available in Asgard. A simple, yet powerful search which gives instant feedback to the user will be crucial to be available on all of the tables that continue to grow as OpenStack users continue to gain more and more historical data. Here is a look at a section of a table with 564 items in it. The user does have the option to sort by any of the columns available in the table, but more powerfully, they can start typing in the filter text box to start weeding down the table items:
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/asgard-search-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Asgard Search 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the user starts typing, the table below is filtered automatically, and quickly:
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/asgard-search-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Asgard Search 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;windows-azure&quot;&gt;Windows Azure&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Azure is overall a very polished UI. One thing that stuck out to me as great inspiration is the simplicity of the wizards in this UI for creating items in your cloud. Although this slickness can be done in many different ways, the Azure designers chose to use vertical blades to show the number of steps and the progress that the user has made through the wizard.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another very nice design decision that the Azure team made was to build responsive forms. As a user navigates through all of the fields for which they need to provide data, the forms are constantly checking for errors inline. The user will notice right away if a field that requires a unique name needs to be changed before they continue filling out the form. It’s a nice time saver for later on when they click the “Create” button and don’t have to go back to the form to figure out which errors may need to be fixed. Take a look at this design in action:
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/azure-wizard-and-form.png&quot; alt=&quot;Azure Wizard and Form&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;paypal-aurora&quot;&gt;PayPal Aurora&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The PayPal designers have done a great job taking the information available via OpenStack and reworking the Information Architecture in their Aurora UI. Take a look at a snapshot of their current navigation structure:
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/aurora-ia.png&quot; alt=&quot;Aurora IA&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only have they grouped things logically in buckets that the user might be looking to act on, but they’ve included breadcrumbs above the working area on the left for users to be able to ground themselves on where they are at any time in the application. This is especially useful if the user has drilled down into a low level details page. Overall, I think this Information Architecture is a huge improvement over the one in Horizon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;cloudstack&quot;&gt;CloudStack&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I personally haven’t had the chance to use CloudStack, but any time I catch a glimpse of the dashboards that are in their UI, I know the designers are doing it right. The information is organized in a clear and concise way without too much clutter. It looks as though the folks working on this UI have done research to figure out what is the most important data to surface to users at a glance, and they’ve left the rest to further drill down detail pages. The visuals are soft are inviting which makes it easy for users to have up on one of their screens throughout the day if needed for monitoring a cloud environment. Here are some of the examples I’ve seen out there:
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/cloudstack-dashboard-1.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;CloudStack Dashboard 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/cloudstack-dashboard-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;CloudStack Dashboard 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;google-compute-engine&quot;&gt;Google Compute Engine&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I hadn’t tried out Google Compute Engine before, so when I gave it a go I was pleasantly surprised at the first time user experience. Rather than dropping the user into an Overview with statistics that are empty considering they haven’t spun up any instances, Google decided to try and push the user in the right direction. They give a few options right off the bat:
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/google-first-time-user-1.png&quot; alt=&quot;Google First Time User 1&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/google-first-time-user-2.png&quot; alt=&quot;Google First Time User 2&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another important decision that Google made was to be sure to give users plenty of information before they decide to take certain actions. For example, when a user tries to delete a project (a pretty huge action), they are given a description of what will happen next if they confirm the action. I think this is a great view into designers thinking about how certain actions will impact users long term:
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/google-delete-project.png&quot; alt=&quot;Google Delete Project&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;amazon-web-services&quot;&gt;Amazon Web Services&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amazon Web Services includes a ton of different applications that a user can take advantage of. They’ve done a great job organizing their information architecture to handle all of these selections. One key design feature they added was to take into consideration the importance of horizontal screen space and to allow the user to hide/show the left hand navigation as needed.
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/aws-dashboard.png&quot; alt=&quot;AWS Dashboard&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dashboard in this view is also something to note. The designers have included a mixture of statistics along with common actions that they know a user will want to take when they jump into this UI.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Are there any features that you’ve seen out there that inspire you to have something better in Horizon? These are definitely some of the things that have caught my eye. Let me know if you have seen any others, I’m happy to log blueprints and put together designs!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Best,
Liz&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/openstack/2014/02/21/horizon-vs-others.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/openstack/2014/02/21/horizon-vs-others.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>openstack</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The OpenStack Years: Maturing the Horizon Overview Page Part 2 - Interaction Design</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was originally written and shared on January 30, 2014 when I was working daily with the OpenStack Community.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After going through an activity to &lt;a href=&quot;https://lizsurette.github.io/openstack/2014/01/27/maturing-horizon-overview-part-1.html&quot;&gt;understand the user and gather a list of requirements&lt;/a&gt;, Ju and I were in great shape to begin designing an Overview page that we could be sure would meet our Horizon users needs. As mentioned in my previous post, Ju played a big role in defining both the users and their requirements, but she continued to participate as I was designing to give feedback along the way as a use case expert.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first step in almost all of my designs includes some sort of sketching and/or whiteboarding. Depending on where I am and if I’m collaboratively designing, I’ll either sketch in my &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.moleskine.com/en/&quot;&gt;Moleskine&lt;/a&gt; or jump into a room with a whiteboard and start drawing. I normally just let my mind go over the requirements and try to capture things on paper/whiteboard as fast as I can, trying to avoid overthinking things. The best thing about drawing on paper or on a whiteboard is that you don’t get too attached to your designs. It’s easy to scrap ideas if you haven’t put a ton of effort into them. Here is a look into the very first ideas that Ju and I came up with for the updated Overview page:
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/overview-sketches.png&quot; alt=&quot;Overview Sketches&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Pretty ugly at this point, right? Yes, I know I don’t have a future as a sketch artist. Well, the ideas are just starting to form at this point and organization and legibility isn’t a huge factor. At this point I’m talking and thinking much faster than my hand can capture. Let me try to translate a bit about the thought process here… We’d like to break down the information that a user would want to see on the Overview page into 3 main sections: Compute, Storage, and Network &amp;amp; Security. It would be great to give the user some visualizations that they can glance at quickly to get an idea of how their environment is performing. Perhaps a mixture of a sparkline to show the trend over time and a bar graph to give the user a picture of the current utilization would be the best way to represent this mix of data. Since this is an Overview page, the user will likely jump off and perform certain actions from this page. It would be nice to have a section of quick links to common actions to support this. There will be additional links and details for certain categories of information that also need to be represented on the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After a good hour of sketching and further discussion with Ju, I took a stab at translating these ideas into wireframes. Wireframes are more solid than sketching, but that doesn’t mean they are a final product. The goal behind wireframes is to get them into a legible format that can be distributed. Wireframes can still be changed very easily. They are not set in stone by any means, but they serve as a great way to get feedback on what certain pieces of the UI could start to look like. For these wireframes, I used Adobe InDesign, although I’ve used a lot of other tools in the past eight years of my design career. A quick side bar on a few of the tools I’ve used and why I’d use them in the future:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;h4 id=&quot;axure&quot;&gt;Axure&lt;/h4&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Great for working on a shared prototype with a group. Can check in /out files to prevent from stepping on each others toes. The output is a clickable HTML prototype which is great for getting a sense of the small interaction details of a design.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;h4 id=&quot;photoshop&quot;&gt;Photoshop&lt;/h4&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Super steep learning curve, but a very powerful tool once you get the basics down. Great for prototyping high-fidelity mockups or even cutting up and editing an existing mockup quickly.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;h4 id=&quot;illustrator&quot;&gt;Illustrator&lt;/h4&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Similar to Photoshop with respect to learning curve. Certain basics like selecting objects isn't consistent with Photoshop which can be frustrating, but a great tool in the end for creating vector designs that may need to scale. I've also used this for print designs with success.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;h4 id=&quot;balsamiq&quot;&gt;Balsamiq&lt;/h4&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Awesome for really quick WISIWIG wireframing/prototyping. Very nice “Sketch” skin that makes it clear these wireframes can be changed easily. There is also a way to change the skin to look a bit more polished if needed. This tool also allows assigning of clickable elements which produces a PDF that acts like a clickable prototype.&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;h4 id=&quot;indesign&quot;&gt;InDesign&lt;/h4&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;The use of masters makes larger sets of designs where elements are reused throughout pages easy to wrangle. Similar to Photoshop and Illustrator with respect to features, but again the slight difference in interactions gives the user yet another learning curve. There is also a way to make elements clickable in an outputted PDF, so this can simulate a prototype.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A big factor in the tool I use is which other designers I’m working with and what tools they are using. I try really hard to sync up with the majority of other designers that I’m working collaboratively and use what they are using. It makes it that much easier to bounce ideas off of each other, share, and reuse designs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After half of a day of translating sketches to wireframes and adding in a few extra details, here is how the first cut panned out:
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/overview-wireframes.png&quot; alt=&quot;Overview Wireframes&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are familiar with Horizon, you will probably first notice that the navigation structure looks a bit different from the current Havana release. We have been experimenting with updating the navigation design and the idea of horizontal navigation just happened to make this set of wireframes, so if you can, ignore the navigation changes for now and focus on the content of this Overview page. As in the early sketches, the wireframe is broken down into 3 sections. The first focuses on Compute information. Users are presented a graph of information showing details for Instances, vCores, vCPUs, and Memory. They can quickly view how many of each of these are currently in use compared to the quota that is allowed. Users can also quickly jump via links to public or private images that are being used by instances. Similarly, the user can view a section for Storage information: specifically Ephemeral, Object, Block, and Snapshot usage and quotas. I decided to break down the larger “Quick Links” area into a list of links specific to each section of data. This breakdown, for example, will make it easier to jump to Storage actions if the user is currently focused on a Storage task. With respect to Network and Security, the user can quickly see the number of Floating IPs both mapped and unmapped as well as the number of Security Groups.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After getting to a solid point with the wireframes, the next step was to reach out to a few different groups for feedback. I &lt;a href=&quot;http://ask-openstackux.rhcloud.com/question/59/improvements-to-horizon-overview/&quot;&gt;reached out&lt;/a&gt; to the UX community for some thoughts. This community is fairly new. I didn’t get much feedback here considering two of the main contributors to the site are Ju and me. Another team that I reached out to for feedback was the Horizon development team. During the weekly meeting I shared my progress and they were excited about the direction of this design. I figured using the weekly meeting would be a more targeted way of getting feedback rather than blasting the entire openstack-dev mailing list, but using the mailing list in the future might be a good way to get more eyes on designs.  Currently, I’m seeking out feedback from end users to validate that these wireframes would meet their needs. I’ve &lt;a href=&quot;http://lists.openstack.org/pipermail/openstack-operators/2014-January/003956.html&quot;&gt;posted&lt;/a&gt; to the openstack-operators mailing list in hopes that some potential users will be able to give some thoughts on these designs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’ve linked to these designs in the Horizon &lt;a href=&quot;https://blueprints.launchpad.net/horizon/+spec/project-overview-page-ceilometer&quot;&gt;blueprint&lt;/a&gt; for this feature. My next steps are to give any design support that is needed (answering questions, updating the design) during the development of this blueprint. After the implementation is done, I want to do some usability testing with end users to be sure it works for them in their work environment. Stay tuned for posts on both of these topics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What do you think about this design? Is there anything missing at an overview level that you would expect to be here for an end user? How about the design process? I’d love to hear if you have any suggestions on improving this as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Best,
Liz&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/openstack/2014/01/30/maturing-horizon-overview-part-2.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/openstack/2014/01/30/maturing-horizon-overview-part-2.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>openstack</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The OpenStack Years: Maturing the Horizon Overview Page Part 1 - Understanding the User and Gathering Requirements</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was originally written and shared on January 27, 2014 when I was working daily with the OpenStack Community.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take a quick look at the current (Havana) Horizon Overview page:
&lt;img src=&quot;https://github.com/lizsurette/lizsurette.github.io/raw/main/static/img/_posts/current-horizon-overview-page.png&quot; alt=&quot;Havana Horizon Overview&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Upon login, non-administrator users are taken to the Project Overview page within &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.openstack.org/developer/horizon/&quot;&gt;Horizon&lt;/a&gt;. Here the user can see a basic set of information about the number of instances, VCPUs, RAM, Floating IPs, and Security Groups that are currently in use in their environment along with the quota that they are allowed. There is also a table that lets the user view the running instances along with a usage summary for the instances shown. The user has the opportunity to filter this table by date range when needed. While this information might cover certain use cases, my colleague &lt;a href=&quot;https://plus.google.com/105626042354015503324/posts&quot;&gt;Ju Lim&lt;/a&gt; and I wanted to take a step back from the current Overview page and think through the type of information that this user of Horizon would want to see when they first log in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now before I go on, this is when &lt;a href=&quot;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Persona_(user_experience)&quot;&gt;Personas&lt;/a&gt; could have &lt;em&gt;REALLY&lt;/em&gt;  helped us. Unfortunately, we hadn’t gotten far enough along with our Persona work within OpenStack to use them, so we had to rely on what we knew from past projects we’ve worked on as well as the data we had from the set of users we had talked to about how they currently use OpenStack. In the coming months, I’ll share the work that we are starting to do in the Persona space, but for now I’d like to note that we plan to revisit these requirements once we have some great Persona data so that we are sure that these completely meet end users needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After reviewing the current state of the Horizon Project Overview page, Ju and I started to brainstorm on how we might improve this page for end users. The goal of this effort was to take this page to the next level of maturity. The big questions that we needed to answer were:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Who is the main end user of this page?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What does this user want and need to see at an Overview level?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Without Personas, we started off by defining the main responsibilities and objectives of the Consumer, the end user of the Overview page:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;As a Consumer, I need to understand the usage of the resources I consume within each project. Due to this, I am concerned with getting a bird’s eye view to the resources within my project. I want to monitor usage data over time so that I can optimize the utilization of my resources.&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;My responsibilities/objectives:&lt;/p&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I’m interested in monitoring usage for the projects that I manage:
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;I want to be able to see usage vs. quota limit.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;I’d like to be able to drill-down in order to view more details.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;I need to be able to troubleshoot an alert to identify root cause.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;I want to analyze usage levels and trends to see if the resource is running out of capacity&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;I’m responsible for managing resources within my project:
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;I can have access to one or more projects but currently have no ability to see an overview page with multiple projects.  I can only switch between projects.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;I interact with project images (create, rename, delete).&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;I launch and terminate instances.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;I attach and detach network interfaces.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;I associate and unassociate Floating IP addresses.&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;I manage key pairs (as needed for object storage).&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After gathering a better understanding of what the primary user looking at the Overview page wants to do, it was important for us to stay focused on the word Overview. As we talked about all of the information that we could &lt;i&gt;potentially&lt;/i&gt; show, we kept a list. Of course, we needed to make sure we kept ourselves honest and took a look through the metrics that are &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.openstack.org/developer/ceilometer/measurements.html&quot;&gt;available in Ceilometer today&lt;/a&gt;. Here is the list of important metrics that we came up with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ul&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Instances&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Public Images&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Private Images&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;vCores&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;vCPUs&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Memory usage&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Ephemeral storage capacity&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Duration of the ephemeral storage&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Object storage capacity&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Objects&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Average object size&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Containers&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Key Pairs&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Block volume capacity&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Block volumes&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Snapshot capacity&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Snapshots&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Backup capacity&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Backups&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Floating IPs Mapped / Allocated&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Floating IPs Unmapped / Unallocated&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Load Balancers&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Security Groups&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Services’ Status – globally and across region (and domain)&lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Alerts&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We took this rough list of metrics and started to discuss each one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What specifically about each would the user be interested in seeing?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;What would the units be?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is this really a piece of information that’s helpful to see at an overview level?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Would it make more sense for the user to drill in further for this information?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Is this a future concept?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We wanted to be sure that our current requirements are attainable. We also started to think about not only the metrics that a user would want to monitor, but what actions would a user want to be able to quickly perform from this view? After a few revisions, we ended up with a more detailed requirement list, organized by metric type:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Summary (Count) of resources
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Instances and Images&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Instances (used / running and available out my quota limit)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Images (aka instance snapshots)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Public Images&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Private Images&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;vCores (used and available)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;vCPUs (used and available)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Memory (used and available)&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Quick Links: Launch a new instance, Launch a new stack&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Storage
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Ephemeral
          &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Ephemeral capacity (used and available)&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Duration of the ephemeral storage&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;/ul&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Object
          &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Object capacity (used and available)&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Number of Objects&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Average object size&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Number of Containers&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Number of Key Pairs&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Quick Links: Create a container, Create a key pair&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;/ul&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Block / Persistent
          &lt;ul&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Block volume capacity (used / active and available)&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Number of Block volumes (used and available)&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Snapshot capacity (used and available)&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Number of Snapshots&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Backup capacity (used and available)&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Number of Backups&lt;/li&gt;
            &lt;li&gt;Quick Links: Create a volume&lt;/li&gt;
          &lt;/ul&gt;
        &lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Network
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Number of Floating IPs&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Number of Mapped / Number of Allocated&amp;lt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Number of Unmapped / Number of Unallocated&amp;lt;&lt;/li&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Number of Load Balancers (currently available on experimental basis)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Security
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Number of Security Groups&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Health
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Services’ Status – globally and across region (and domain)&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;Alerts
      &lt;ul&gt;
        &lt;li&gt;Number of Alerts&lt;/li&gt;
      &lt;/ul&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There. A nice organized list of metrics that we want to design towards. Do you have any feedback on this list of requirements as it exists so far? I’m always looking to improve requirements and designs based on user feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, keep an eye out for my next post in the “Maturing the Overview page in Horizon&quot; series where I walk through the design phase of this effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Best,
Liz&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 27 Jan 2014 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/openstack/2014/01/27/maturing-horizon-overview-part-1.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/openstack/2014/01/27/maturing-horizon-overview-part-1.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>openstack</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The OpenStack Years: Which groups in OpenStack do User Experience designers influence today?</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was originally written and shared on December 16, 2013 when I was working daily with the OpenStack Community.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before I jump into blog posts about OpenStack user experience requirements, designs, and user testing, I wanted to start with some level setting and explain some of the groups that have been a focus in the user experience space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;user-experience&quot;&gt;User Experience&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To start, let me give a quick introduction to the way user experience design currently works within OpenStack. How do we as user experience professionals work within the OpenStack community? Today, we work very closely with the Horizon and TripleO/Tuskar teams. We attend the weekly IRC meetings, participate in feature requirement discussions, register blueprints, report bugs, design wireframes for new features, and test existing features with users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;User experience isn’t an official program in OpenStack, but a few of us have started to form a team around the efforts in the UX space. We now have an &lt;a href=&quot;http://ask-openstackux.rhcloud.com/questions/&quot;&gt;Ask OpenStack UX&lt;/a&gt; site where we house design discussions. Weekly, we send out an update to the mailing list on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://lists.openstack.org/pipermail/openstack-dev/2013-December/020935.html\&quot;&gt;current topics&lt;/a&gt; that are being discussed. As a group we are continuously improving our processes. We are discussing the option of moving to and using the &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/openstack-infra/storyboard\&quot;&gt;StoryBoard&lt;/a&gt; tool that Thierry Carrez proposed at the Hong Kong summit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How could you contribute to the user experience effort in OpenStack? Join us in discussions on Ask OpenStack UX, share your wireframes, give your feedback as an OpenStack user, or simply give your thoughts on how we could improve our way of working. You can find us in #openstack-ux on Freenode if you’d like to chat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;horizon&quot;&gt;Horizon&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I mentioned in &lt;a href=&quot;https://lizsurette.github.io/openstack/2013/12/12/openstack-an-introduction.html&quot;&gt;my first blog post&lt;/a&gt;, Horizon is where I jumped into the OpenStack world. This is the only user interface that is currently shipped with the core OpenStack product and it seems obvious to me that others will have the same experience. The Horizon Dashboard gives the user a visual way to perform basic OpenStack tasks like spinning up an Instance and assigning that instance a floating IP. Of course, the user can do these things from the command line interface (CLI), but the UI is where most of the user experience work that has been done so far has been focused.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Horizon development team is a great bunch to work with and are extremely supportive of making sure this component has great user experience design. Currently, Horizon only supports the other core components, but developers are welcomed to add plugins to Horizon for components they are working on outside of the core.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are a few options that I know about for quickly getting access to a running version of Horizon if you’d like to poke around and test things out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;http://trystack.org/ - You can get a free account by joining their Facebook group. Once you’ve been added to the group, simply use your Facebook credentials for authentication and you’ll be able to view the Horizon UI.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;http://www.stacklab.org/ - This is another quick way to get access to Horizon to poke around.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;If you are feeling brave and would like to get your own environment up and running – Spin up a RHEL-based Linux distro in a VM and run through the &lt;a href=&quot;http://openstack.redhat.com/Quickstart&quot;&gt;Quick Start guide&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Another way to get a development environment up and running would be to use http://devstack.org/&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you are interested in jumping into the development or review side of Horizon, feel free to come to one of our &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Meetings#Horizon_team_meeting&quot;&gt;weekly meetings on IRC&lt;/a&gt; to get a feel for what we are working on today. Also, getting started with Horizon can be done by following the &lt;a href=&quot;http://docs.openstack.org/developer/horizon/quickstart.html&quot;&gt;quick start instructions&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tripleo&quot;&gt;TripleO&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my introductory &lt;a href=&quot;https://lizsurette.github.io/openstack/2013/12/12/openstack-an-introduction.html&quot;&gt;Why a blog? Who is the intended audience of this blog?&lt;/a&gt;, I mentioned that I quickly realized that installation and deployment are big areas in which the usability of OpenStack could be improved. &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/TripleO&quot;&gt;TripleO&lt;/a&gt; and Tuskar work together to tackle just this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;TripleO is a program aimed at installing, upgrading and operating OpenStack clouds using OpenStack’s own cloud facilities as the foundations - building on nova, neutron and heat to automate fleet management at data center scale. (https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/TripleO)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a bit of a mind bending concept, but I highly recommend watching Robert Collins’ &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RjUvpfzejtU&amp;amp;ab_channel=OpenInfrastructureFoundation&quot;&gt;talk from the Portland OpenStack Summit&lt;/a&gt;. Although TripleO continues to evolve with each release, I found this talk to be a great introduction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;tuskar&quot;&gt;Tuskar&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We haven’t worked on any user experience designs specifically for TripleO, but this is where &lt;a href=&quot;https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/TripleO/Tuskar&quot;&gt;Tuskar&lt;/a&gt; comes into play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Tuskar gives administrators the ability to control how and where OpenStack services are deployed across the data center. Using Tuskar, administrators divide hardware into “resource classes” that allow predictable elastic scaling as cloud demands grow. This resource orchestration allows Tuskar users to ensure SLAs, improve performance, and maximize utilization across the data center. (https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/TripleO/Tuskar)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tuskar has recently combined efforts with the TripleO program and is bringing a user interface into the mix. Although there are &lt;a href=&quot;http://lists.openstack.org/pipermail/openstack-dev/2013-December/021388.html&quot;&gt;huge discussions&lt;/a&gt; currently taking place about the requirements for the Icehouse release of Tuskar working with TripleO, a demo of the initial concepts shown at the Hong Kong Summit can be seen &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VEY035-Lyzo&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, TripleO and Tuskar will work together to provide a community solution for installing and deploying an OpenStack environment solving a huge need for the end users of OpenStack!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thoughts?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Mon, 16 Dec 2013 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/openstack/2013/12/16/openstack-user-experience-influence.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/openstack/2013/12/16/openstack-user-experience-influence.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>openstack</category>
        
      </item>
    
      <item>
        <title>The OpenStack Years: Why a blog?</title>
        <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This was originally written and shared on December 12, 2013 when I was working daily with the OpenStack Community.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I should start off with an introduction. I’m Liz and I’ve been working for Red Hat for just over a year. I work on the User Experience Design team with a focus on the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.openstack.org/&quot;&gt;OpenStack&lt;/a&gt; project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since I started working at Red Hat I’ve been working on the OpenStack project. That means I’ve been involved with the project for almost a year now. So why has it taken me a year to decide to start this blog? Well, there has definitely been a learning curve. With everything that I’ve done in the OpenStack space, I’ve tried to take the view point of the OpenStack customer or end user. I started off very small in the OpenStack world by installing the latest release (which was Folsom at the time). I realized that there wasn’t one solid way to go about installing OpenStack, so I spent a lot of my days hacking around and getting something up and running. Ultimately, I ended up getting a development environment running on Fedora 19 using &lt;a href=&quot;http://devstack.org/&quot;&gt;DevStack&lt;/a&gt;. As many other people in the OpenStack community have already done, I came to the conclusion that installation and deployment should be high on the priority list when it comes to improving the usability of OpenStack.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once I got access to a running version of OpenStack, I spent time reviewing the Horizon Dashboard. Although the usability field doesn’t have to be limited to user interfaces, it was a great place for me to start. I needed to get familiar with what features were offered in OpenStack and what better way to do this than to try the features out myself. Come to find out later that there are actually features in OpenStack that aren’t surfaced in the UI. I had no idea they even existed at this point. I went about reviewing the dashboard and I logged a fair amount of bugs in &lt;a href=&quot;https://bugs.launchpad.net/horizon/+bugs&quot;&gt;Launchpad&lt;/a&gt;. Most of the bugs were small, but a few were for some larger usability issues that would be great to solve. I was so excited to see a few of these bugs get picked up and fixed right away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was lucky enough to be able to attend my first OpenStack Summit as we planned for the Grizzly release in Portland, OR. Getting to meet the majority of the Horizon community in person was awesome. I realized during this Summit just how passionate and supportive this group of people are working together on OpenStack. I was so happy to be a part of this. As I’ve continued my work on OpenStack and have become more familiar with the processes, I’ve stepped up the amount of work that I’ve been able to contribute to the project. I’ve done work on creating use cases, developing personas, sketching, wireframing, and user testing. I’ve shared my work via e-mails, conversations over IRC, or documents and spreadsheets that have been created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I look back over the last year’s worth of work, I realize that I’ve influenced a lot of small features, but it takes some time to compile the list of items I’ve completed. As I move forward with my OpenStack work, I’d like to make sure that I take some time with each of the tasks I work on to do a small write up of what I’m working on and why it’s important to the OpenStack community. I hope this blog will generate further discussion and help improve the usability of OpenStack even more than if I simply share my work via e-mail and IRC.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another goal of this blog is for it to serve as a history of some of the usability topics that have been discussed in the OpenStack community. It would be great if my posts sparked some conversations about moving certain features forward. I definitely won’t confine my posts to just UI topics, so as I start to explore some of the ways that user experience professionals can influence things like APIs and the command line, I hope others find my discoveries helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thoughts?&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Thu, 12 Dec 2013 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
        <link>http://localhost:4000/openstack/2013/12/12/openstack-an-introduction.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://localhost:4000/openstack/2013/12/12/openstack-an-introduction.html</guid>
        
        
        <category>openstack</category>
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
